你回来啦  电影看得怎么样
Hi, how was the screening?
谢尔顿搬出罗莎·帕克斯
Oh, Sheldon invoked Rosa Parks
黑人民权女运动者
因为拒绝公车司机要求黑人给白人让座的要求而被捕
来让某个插队的人感到愧疚
to make somebody who cut the line feel bad,
结果只让在场白人感到愧疚
but only the white people felt bad.
我就不该给他买那本
Ugh, I should've never bought him that coloring book
美国每年2月是黑人历史月
以表示对非裔黑人历史的尊重与贡献
解释黑人历史月的着色本
that explains Black History Month.
你跟我妈处得怎么样
How'd it go with my mother?
一开始有些不顺
Uh, you know, it started a little rocky,
但我们现在已经处得挺好
but I think we got to a good place.
真棒
Well done.
我送她到酒店的时候
Yeah, and when I dropped her off at the hotel,
她还给了我一个拥抱
she even gave me a hug.
她以为你噎到要施行海姆立克法吗
Did she think you were choking or...
我抬杠呢  很棒啊
I'm sorry, that's great.
谢谢你花时间陪她
Thank you for spending time with her.
小事一桩
No problem.
对了
Um, so listen,
我不知道你接下来这周末有何安排
I don't know if you have any plans next weekend,
但我答应了你母亲
but I kind of promised your mom
我们会再办个婚礼
we'd have another wedding ceremony
好让她这次能出席
so she could attend this time.
等等  我们要再结一次婚吗
Wait, we're gonna get married again?
算吧  但这次我们就能邀请亲朋好友来啦
Yeah, kind of, but now we can invite our friends and family.
这一个拥抱代价有点大吧
Seems like a lot of trouble for a hug.
别这样  会很有意思
Come on, it'll be fun,
而且你妈妈也真的很伤心
and, you know, your mom was genuinely hurt
我们第一次婚礼没邀请她去
we didn't invite her to the first one.
我得为我们辩解下
Look, in our defense,
我们当时是一时兴起才去结婚的
it was kind of a spur of the moment thing,
而且我们不喜欢她啊
and also, we don't like her.
莱纳德  她可是你妈妈
Leonard, come on, she's your mom.
如果我们能做件事讨她开心
If we can do something to make her happy,
那为什么不做
why wouldn't we?
我才说过理由啊
I just said why--
我们不喜欢她
we don't like her.
那好  那别想着是为了她
Hey, look, then forget about her,
就当是为了我们自己
let's do it for us.
办一个简单又不会太隆重的就行
We could keep it small and informal.
这次我们能邀请自己的家人
This time we can invite our families.
你哥哥出狱了吗
Is your brother out of prison?
对啊  监狱人满为患  提早获释
Thanks to overcrowding, yeah.
我爸要是来就好了
I'd love it if my dad could come.
我们可以邀请他啊
Oh, you have to invite him.
他们离婚后我就没见过他了
I haven't seen him since the divorce.
他整个人都不一样了
Oh, he's like a different man.
人不抽抽了
He stopped twitching,
他好像还长高了4公分呢
and I think he grew an inch and a half.
那就这么定啦
Well, then it's settled.
天啊  真有意思
God. So funny.
从来没想到我的二婚对象会是你
I never thought my second marriage would be to you!
不是什么有法律效力的婚礼
Okay, so it's not a legal ceremony,
只是一个我们重说婚誓
it's just a chance for us to redo our vows
好让大家能在一旁观礼的机会
so everyone can be part of it.
所以不会有伴娘
So there's no maid of honor?
不会
No.
但如果我那天要穿鸡心领的
But if I were to, say, wear a purple satin dress
紫色绸缎小礼服  而且站在你旁边
with a sweetheart neckline and stand near you,
你也没办法阻止我  对吧
you wouldn't be able to stop me, right?
你要这样  我也没招啊
I don't see how I could.
那我就却之不恭了
Then I graciously accept.
婚礼由谁来主持呢
Who's going to officiate?
我还希望由你主持呢
I was kind of hoping you would.
等等  所以我只是没啥鸟用的伴娘吗
Wait, now I'm just some lousy maid of honor?
好消息  我刚跟我妈说完电话
Hey, good news, I just got off the phone with my mother.
她会出席这场婚礼
She is coming to the wedding.
好  等等
Okay, wait,
你在邀请人来参加我们的婚礼吗
you're inviting people to our wedding?
对啊  我在邀请人来参加"我们"的婚礼
Yes, I'm inviting people to our wedding.
我已经邀请了
Yeah, I've already asked
史蒂芬·霍金教授与小罗伯特·唐尼
Stephen Hawking and Robert Downey Jr.
还有一个人  你们期望别太高  他很忙
And now, don't get your hopes up, 'cause he's pretty busy,
是厄爾諾·魯比克
but Erno Rubik.
他是谁啊
Who's Erno Rubik?
不是吧
Seriously?
魯比克的方块[魔方]就是他发明的
He invented the Rubik's Cube.
好吧  行
Okay, fine,
但你为什么要邀请他来我们的婚礼
but why would you invite him to our wedding?
因为尽管他名利尽收
Because, despite his fame and fortune,
但我感觉到他是很寂寞的人
he strikes me as a lonely man.
你真的很贴心
Well, it's very sweet of you
为了莱纳德的妈妈这么费心费力
to go to all this trouble for Leonard's mother.
我也是为了莱纳德
Yeah, I'm also doing it for Leonard.
我觉得这应该能改善他们的关系
I think this could really help their relationship.
请你老子不用先问过老娘的吗
How dare you invite your father without consulting me!
对不起  但是我不觉得邀请我爸
Sorry, but I don't think I need your permission
来参加我的婚礼  需要经过你的同意
to have my father at my wedding.
你知道我跟他婚姻破碎是因为
You do understand our marriage ended
他外遇了吧
because he had an affair.
我知道  这事万般不应该
I know, and there's no excuse for that.
他说我冷血  伤他男性自尊
He claimed I was cold, emasculating,
多年来对他未曾表达过任何肉体上的亲近
and hadn't shown him any physical affection for years.
我错了  万般不应该中有三个应该
I was wrong, there's three excuses for that.
天啊
Oh, my God.
成功了
It's working.
你确定吗
You sure?
你看
Look.
系统能维持自己的稳定性
The system is maintaining its own stability,
量子涡旋装置现在在自控方向
the quantum vortex apparatus is now controlling the orientation.
真的呢
You're right.
你知道这意味着什么吗
You realize what this means?
我知道
I do.
这就是概念的验证
It's proof of concept.
我们做出了切实可行的导向系统
We've got a workable guidance system.
恭喜你
Congratulations.
谢谢你
Thanks!
我收到了美国空军发来的电邮
Hey, I just got an e-mail from the U.S. Air Force.
打开看看
Open it.
"我们希望能尽早跟您见面
"We request a meeting at your earliest convenience
谈谈你的量子导向系统
regarding your quantum guidance system,
临时专利编号是62/295118"
provisional patent 62/295118."
奇了怪了
That's weird.
这里面有我们不知道的暗窗吗
Is there a window around here we don't know about?
我觉得应该只是巧合吧
I'm sure it's just a coincidence.
当然啦
Yeah, of course.
不然还能是为什么
What else could it be?
妈呀  我真是爱死美国啦
Boy, do I love America.
谢谢你来接我
Thank you for picking me up.
不客气
Oh, you're welcome.
我是在对你的伴说
I was speaking to your young lady.
这是我的荣幸  库珀女士
My pleasure, Mrs. Cooper.
叫我玛丽就好了
Oh, please call me Mary.
好吧  玛丽
Okay, Mary.
这我听了不太舒服
You know, that doesn't work for me,
还是就叫库珀女士吧
let's stay with Mrs. Cooper.
谢尔顿  别犯傻
Sheldon, don't be silly.
怎么了
Wait, what?
我跟你不熟之前  也是这么叫你的啊
That's what I called you till I got to know you better.
莱纳德跟佩妮还邀请我  真是太好了
It was so nice of Leonard and Penny to invite me.
其实呢  是我...
Well, actually, I...
绝对是啊
It sure was.
莱纳德在我心里也很特别
I've always had a special place in my heart for Leonard.
他这些年来一直照顾着我的宝贝
Taking care of my baby all these years.
不好意思
Excuse me,
是我照顾他好吗
I take care of him.
你说是就是啦
Sure you do.
还有谁要来参加这典礼啊
So who else is coming to this shindig?
就我们那群人
Oh, well, the usual gang.
佩妮的家人明天来
Penny's family is coming tomorrow.
莱纳德的母亲已经到了
Yeah, and Leonard's mother's already here.
贝弗莉啊
Oh, Beverly.
真"好"
How nice.
你们见过  对吧
You've met her, right?
是的  见过
Yes, I have.
妈  她是无神论者  又不是吸血鬼
Mother, she's an atheist, not a vampire.
无论哪种身份  麻烦停下车我要买大蒜驱邪
Either way, let's stop and get some garlic.
玛丽  你最近过得如何
So, Mary, how have you been?
多谢关心
Well, thank you so much for asking.
我过得很好  你呢
I've been well, and you?
-非常好  -那就好
- Very good. - Good.
我不知道我们有什么好担心的
I don't know what we were worried about;
她们俩相处得十分融洽
they're getting along great.
谢尔顿告诉我  你的丈夫也会来
Sheldon tells me your husband's coming.
是我的前夫
My ex-husband.
真遗憾
Oh, I'm so sorry.
-不必  -那行
- Don't be. - All right.
气氛降至冰点
Whew, chilly.
冷得都能看见我呼出来的气了
I think I can see my breath.
我们听得见哦
We can hear you.
-抱歉  -抱歉
- Sorry. - Sorry.
我真是好傻好天真
I can't believe I was so naive.
军方肯定会
The military is just gonna
拿走整个项目
take over the whole project.
如果我们拒绝  后果不用想都知道
And you know what happens if we object?
我们会"被消失"
We disappear.
彻底人间蒸发
Like off the map.
就像《美国偶像》第四季之后的每一位冠军[都不红]
Like every American Idol winner since season four.
拜托  霍华德  你反应过度了
Come on, Howard, you're overreacting.
是吗
Am I?
是这样吗
要不要打个赌  某个秘密行动组的家伙
Wha-- what do you want to bet some black ops guy
正在重印我的高中毕业纪念册
is reprinting my high school yearbook
而新版本已经没我了
and I'm no longer in it?
那张象棋俱乐部合照
That chess club picture is now
现在就剩大卫·齐默尔曼和伊莱恩·周了
just David Zimmerman and Elaine Cho.
听着  我打开了空军的官网
Okay, look, I'm on the Air Force Web site,
发邮件给你的那个部门
and the department that e-mailed you
是专门负责收购的
is in charge of acquisitions.
或许他们只是想花大钱买你的发明
So maybe they just want to give you a lot of money for your invention.
拜托  事情肯定不是这样子
Oh, please, that's not how it works.
你也看过《E.T.》《阿凡达》《侏罗纪世界》吧
You saw  E.T., Avatar, Jurassic World.
军方就是跑来接管一切的恶霸
The military just shows up and takes over.
你应该知道那些都不是纪录片吧
You do realize those weren't documentaries, right?
不好意思  你觉得很好笑吗
I'm sorry, you find this funny?
不啊  我只是在回味《侏罗纪世界》
No, I was just thinking about Jurassic World.
那真是部烂片
Boy, that was terrible.
我们得走楼梯
Oh, we have to use the stairs.
电梯什么时候能修好
When are they gonna fix your elevator?
我不知道  随时吧
Uh... I don't-- any day now.
走楼梯也行
Well, the stairs are fine.
再说了  你妈就在楼上
Besides, your mother is up there.
或许我走着走着心脏病发
Maybe I'll have a heart attack
就不用见她了
and not have to see her.
我知道你和老妈的关系
Hey, I, I know things are a little rough
有点僵
with you and Mom,
但我真的很高兴你能来
but I'm really glad you're here.
我也是
Me, too.
我真不应该做血管修复术
I should have never had that angioplasty
因为完全没有要病发的样子
because I feel fine.
佩妮很期待能见到你
Penny's really looking forward to seeing you.
她是个可人儿
Ah, she's a sweetie.
你娶了一个好老婆  莱纳德
You got a good one there, Leonard.
多谢  爸爸
Thanks, Dad.
你是怎么娶到好老婆的啊
How the hell did you do that?
真是和乐融融啊
Isn't this nice?
我们到了
Hey, we're here.
阿尔弗雷德
Alfred!
感谢你能来
Thank you for coming!
很高兴能来
Well, happy to be here.
-恭喜你们  -谢谢
- And congratulations. - Thank you.
爸爸  这是谢尔顿
Dad, you remember Sheldon.
霍夫斯塔德博士
Dr. Hofstadter.
库珀博士
Dr. Cooper.
这是谢尔顿的母亲  玛丽
This is Sheldon's mother, Mary.
你好
How do you do?
很高兴见到你
Nice to meet you.
这是他的女朋友  艾米
And his girlfriend, Amy.
你好
A pleasure.
Hi.
当然  还有我妈
And, of course, Mom.
你好  可憎的悍妇
Hello, my hateful shrew.
你也好  皱巴巴的老王八蛋
Hello to you, you wrinkled old bastard.
好吧  现在我能感觉到气氛有点紧张了
All right, now I'm starting to sense a little tension.
行了  你们俩不要开吵
All right, you two, don't start.
我和佩妮是为了你们才再办一次婚礼
Penny and I are throwing this second wedding for your benefit.
拜托不要毁了它好吗
Can you please not ruin it?
当然  很抱歉
Of course. I'm sorry.
瞧瞧  原来你会道歉啊
Oh, look at that-- you can apologize.
妈
Mom!
抱歉
I'm sorry.
《圣经》说宽恕...
You know, the Bible says forgiveness...
妈
Mom!
抱歉
I'm sorry.
饿了吧
Uh, who's hungry?
我们在城里最棒的餐厅订了位哦
We have a reservation at the best restaurant in town.
那餐厅在点评网上只有三颗半星
It only got three-and-a-half stars on Yelp.
谢尔顿
Sheldon!
我不觉得抱歉  我说的是事实
I'm not sorry. That's true.
我不知道该怎么办
I don't know what to do.
对方可是美国空军
It's the Air Force.
我是该回复这封邮件
I mean, should I respond to their e-mail?
还是置之不理
Ignore it?
你不能置之不理
You can't ignore it.
这又不是牙医发来让你回去做检查的贺卡
It's not that postcard that says it's time to go back to the dentist.
小哥俩  走吧
Guys, come on.
我们约了大家吃饭呢
We're meeting everyone for dinner.
稍等  我就怕万一我回复了
One sec. I'm just afraid if I respond,
他们就知道我的项目成功了
then they'll know I got it.
伙计
Oh, dude.
你点开邮件的那一刻
The minute you opened that e-mail,
他们就知道你成功了
they knew you got it.
没准他们现在就通过
I mean, they're probably looking at you
电脑的摄像头监视你呢
through the camera right now.
我勒个去
Oh, damn.
我爱美国哟
I love America.
你们闹够了没有
Are you done with this nonsense?
这不是闹着玩的
It's not nonsense.
美国军方就是这么办事儿的
This is how the U.S. Military works.
就算是美国军方好了
Oh, if it's even the U.S. Military.
那也可以是假装成美方的外国军方势力
It could be foreign military pretending to be American.
你说得对  我们一旦把导向系统给了他们
You're right. We turn our guidance system over to them,
他们会立即拿来对付美国
next thing we know, they're using it against us.
我也爱美国的敌人们哟
I also love the enemies of America.
佩妮  希望我和莱纳德父亲的
Penny, I hope the example of my failed marriage
失败婚姻并没有让你
to Leonard's father doesn't discourage you
对你俩的婚姻失去信心
from the commitment you've made to one another.
当然不会
Oh, of course not.
不过我和阿尔弗雷德的感情比你们的深厚
Although Alfred and I had a lot more going for us than you two.
妈  多留几句"好话"祝酒时说吧
Mom, please save something for the toast.
阿尔弗雷德  你是做什么的
So, Alfred, what is it that you do for a living?
我是一名人类学家
Oh, I'm an anthropologist.
我研究古人和古文化
I study ancient peoples and cultures.
老天  就是史前大洪水之前的一切吗
My goodness, so all the way back to the Flood.
《圣经》中记载了挪亚时代发生的全球大洪水
也就是诺亚方舟故事的由来
别笑  她刚不是开玩笑
Don't laugh-- she wasn't joking.
玩你的手机  别多事
Play with your phone.
关于这一点
Well, on that note,
在很多不同国家的文化中  他们的神话里
there are many cultures that have an apocalyptic flood
都有过末日大洪水的记载
as part of their mythology.
我不信神话
I don't have a mythology.
我只信永远正确的上帝之话
I have the unerring Word of God.
但你说的非常有意思
But that's very interesting.
我没有看不起你的信仰的意思
I-I didn't mean to disparage your faith.
其实我挺欣赏的
Actually, I admire it.
-真的吗  -当然
- Really? - Yes.
我自己是不可知论者
Yes, I'm an agnostic myself,
但我曾祷告过很多次  祈求上帝
but I have prayed, many times, to God,
将我妻子变成一根盐柱
to turn my wife into a pillar of salt.
也算接近了吧
Well, He came close.
把她变成一块大冰块
Turned her into a giant block of ice.
霍华德  大学里肯定可以找到
Howard, there must be someone at the university
能帮你的人吧
you can go to for help.
开什么玩笑
Are you kidding?
没准就是他们先把消息
They're probably the ones who leaked it
透漏给军方的
to the military in the first place.
那第四台新闻里那哥们呢
What about the guy on the Channel Four News?
总说"第四与你同一阵线"
You know, "Four on Your Side"?
也许他也可以来你的阵线
Maybe he can be on your side.
我是被政府骚扰
I'm being harassed by the government,
不是想弄清诈骗骗局真相
not trying to get to the bottom of a dog-walking scam.
够了
Oh, stop!
你知道真相是什么吗
You know what's really happening?
所有你看过的电影
All the movies you've watched,
电视剧  漫画书
the TV shows, the comic books--
将你的想法彻底扭曲了
they've completely twisted your thinking.
没人在追查你  没人在监听你
No one's after you, no one's listening to you,
根本没人在乎你
no one cares about you.
我还是希望
I'd like to think
"第四与你同一阵线"那哥们是在乎我的
the "Four on Your Side" guy cares about me.
贝弗莉  我知道你和阿尔弗雷德
You know, Beverly, I know you and Alfred
有你们的分歧  但其实你想一下
have your differences, but if you think about it,
如果你没嫁给他  就不会有莱纳德了
if you hadn't married him, there'd be no Leonard.
所以也是好事  对不对
So that's good, right?
对吧
Yeah.
前面是霍华德吗
Is that Howard in front of us?
好像是
Oh, maybe.
跟上他们
Get closer.
天啊
Oh, God.
好像有人跟踪我们
I think someone's following us.
你在自己脑补
You're being ridiculous.
真不是我脑补  他就跟在后面
I'm not being ridiculous-- he's right on my tail.
在这左转  看他们会不会跟着转
Uh, turn left here and see if he turns with us.
他为什么在这转弯
Well, why is he turning here?
饭店在另一边
The restaurant's the other way.
不知道
I don't know.
他有用一款路况软件  可能前头出车祸了吧
He uses that traffic app. Maybe there's an accident.
那跟他走吧
Oh, so follow him.
不好
Oh, no!
我就说吧
I told you!
可能只是巧合而已
It's probably just a coincidence.
加点速  看他会不会跟上来
Speed up a little, see if he stays with you.
你快点开
Well, go faster.
要跟丢了
You're losing him.
他怎么那么急
What is his hurry?
这样  你闪一下车灯
You know what, flash your lights.
让他知道是你
Let him know it's you.
他在闪灯
He's flashing his lights.
那是什么意思
What's that mean?
他好像想让我们靠边停
I-I think he wants us to pull over.
不许靠边停
Do not pull over!
我才不要当单亲妈妈
I'm not raising this baby alone!
坐稳了
Hang on!
你丈夫去世以后
So, after your husband passed,
你没有再嫁吗
you never remarried?
没有  全情投入在工作和教堂上了
No, just focused on work and the church.
你是做什么工作的
Ah. And what do you do?
在教堂工作
I work at the church.
有你在  是他们三生有幸
Well, they're lucky to have you.
谢谢
Well, thank you.
不客气
You're welcome.
你看出来是怎么回事了吗
Do you realize what's happening here?
当然了
Yeah, I do.
他们面包吃太多  一会该吃不下饭了
They're filling up on bread and ruining their meal.
你们怎么那么晚
What took you guys so long?
我们本来跟着霍华德来着  但不知道怎么
Oh, we were following Howard, but for some reason,
他把车灯关掉逆着单行道走了
he turned off his headlights and went up a one-way street.
你们聊什么了
So, what did we miss?
不过是我和玛丽彼此了解一下
Oh, just Mary and I getting to know each other a little.
莱纳德  你父亲真是讨人喜欢
Leonard, your father is just charming.
他还破产了
He's also broke.
他没有告诉你吗
Did he mention that?
好的  妈  你去那边坐
Okay, Mom, you sit over there...
我给伯纳黛特打电话  问问怎么这么久
And I'm gonna call Bernadette and see what's keeping them.
我要是早知道你破产了
If I'd known you were broke,
就不会那么在意你多吃面包了
I wouldn't have made a big deal about the bread.
佩妮
Hey, Penny.
你说什么呢
What are you talking about?
刚刚那是你啊
Oh, that was you?
说来话长
Long story.
你们先吃吧
Why don't you go ahead and eat.
我们恐怕还要一会儿呢
We're gonna be a while.
我跟你说  我没嗑药
I'm telling you, I'm not on drugs.
是政府要抓我
The government's out to get me!
最近一个比较有趣的新发现
Now, one of the more exciting things to be found recently
就是尼安德塔人[穴居人]
is that Neanderthals
与智人[现代人类祖先]  常会与彼此交配
and Homosapiens frequently mated with each other.
这下我就明白
Well, that certainly explains
为什么我会嫁给谢尔顿的父亲了
my marriage to Sheldon's father.
非常好笑  因为我父亲不是特别聪明的人
That's funny, because my father was not a very clever man.
没有你"我什么都听不懂了"
I'd be lost without you.
我想邀大家举杯
Uh, I would like to propose a toast
敬我的妻子兼准新娘
to my wife and bride-to-be.
你看  这句好笑的点在...
See, that's funny because...
玩你手机去
Back to your phone.
佩妮
Penny...
我爱你  这点毋庸置疑
I've always known I loved you,
但过去的这一年让我意识到
but this last year has shown me
我也爱上了活在围城里的感觉
that I also love being married to you.
谢谢你愿意嫁给我
Thank you for saying yes.
谢谢你始终没放弃
Oh, thanks for asking until I did.
说得好
Hear, hear.
干杯
Cheers.
我也想举杯
I, uh, I would also like to make a toast.
莱纳德
Leonard,
我很高兴  看到你找到了一位
I am so happy that you have found a woman
爱你又关心你的女人
who loves and cares for you.
你什么意思给老娘讲清楚
What the hell is that supposed to mean?
你该吃药了
Why don't you take a pill?
就像你上床之前那样吗
Like you did before sex?
其实当时我最想要的是眼罩
What I really needed was a blindfold.
好了  各位
All right, everyone...
冷静点
calm down.
我们想想《圣经》里是怎么说的
Let's all remember what it says in the Bible:
"不轻易发怒的
"He who is slow to anger
胜过勇士"
is better than the mighty."
你这女人  能看看别的书吗
Oh, dear woman, can you please read another book?
只要上帝出新作  我就追
When God writes one, I will.
如果谁想点舒芙蕾吃
Um, if-if we want to order the souffle
现在可以点了
we might want to get on that.
莱纳德  希望你别介意  我有些累了
Leonard, if you don't mind, I-I think I'm a little tired.
今晚就到这里吧
I'm gonna call it a night.
当然不介意  爸爸
Sure, Dad.
我也有些累坏了
I'm a little tuckered out myself,
各位明早见
so I will see you all in the morning.
愿意跟我一起打车吗
Would you like to share a cab?
当然好
That would be fine.
你在哪住
Where are you staying?
威斯汀酒店
I'm at the Westin.
我也是
Oh, so am I.
能请你喝杯睡前酒吗
Can I interest you in a nightcap?
当然可以
I think that you could.
那是怎么回事
What is happening there?
我觉得再明显不过了
I think it's pretty obvious.
他们不想吃甜点  因为吃了一肚子面包
They don't want dessert 'cause they filled up on bread.
她还是不接
She's still not answering.
我爸也没回信息
My father's not texting me back.
因为他们都关机了啊
'Cause they both turned their phones off.
我一点都不喜欢这样
I don't like this at all.
我也不喜欢
I don't like it either.
真的吗
Really?
可我爱死了
'Cause I love it.